Subject Files
Marist Archives and Special Collections
- Subject Files, 2.1.3.6
  - Subject files: Famous First Flights [proposed photographs for use in book], 1920 - 1963; 1 (Box 1544)
    - Verso: p. 364 September 1926 National Geographic from Admiral Byrd; Chapter VIII; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 13-verso
    - Air Force Museum, Wright-Patterson; Douglas World Cruisers lined up and ready for start of flight after christening; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 14
    - Verso: Air Force Museum, Wright-Patterson; Douglas World Cruisers lined up and ready for start of flight after christening; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 14-verso
    - Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 15
    - Verso: Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 15-verso
    - Chapter 16, Pix No.1 Just before the "Polecat" took off, the President of the Flight Safety Foundation, Gen. Joseph D. Caldara USAF (ret.) presented the Foundation's certificate of endorsement to Flight Commanders Fred L. Austin and Harrison Finch (rear) and Col. Willard F. Rockwell whose firm sponsored the Double Pole journey; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 16
    - Verso: Chapter 16, Pix No.1 Just before the "Polecat" took off, the President of the Flight Safety Foundation, Gen. Joseph D. Caldara USAF (ret.) presented the Foundation's certificate of endorsement to Flight Commanders Fred L. Austin and Harrison Finch (rear) and Col. Willard F. Rockwell whose firm sponsored the Double Pole journey; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 16-verso
    - Capetown, South Africa - crews of both C-130's shortly before departure on historic non-stop flight from Capetown, to McMurdo Sound, Antarctica. L/R front row, LCDR. R.G. Dickerson (plane commander of lead plane) Radm. James R. Reedy, CDR. G.R. Kelly USN, Commanding officer VX-6, LCDR. W.B. Kurlak, plane commander of second plane; U.S. Naval Photographic Center; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 17
    - Verso: Capetown, South Africa - crews of both C-130's shortly before departure on historic non-stop flight from Capetown, to McMurdo Sound, Antarctica. L/R front row, LCDR. R.G. Dickerson (plane commander of lead plane) Radm. James R. Reedy, CDR. G.R. Kelly USN, Commanding officer VX-6, LCDR. W.B. Kurlak, plane commander of second plane; U.S. Naval Photographic Center; Doubleday & Company, Inc., 277 Park Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017, Title: Famous First Flights, 17-verso
    - When they crashed. Ray had affixed 2 car radiators bolted together overland car radiators were used at Moulmein Burma. This was taken in Sydney, 18
    - Verso: When they crashed. Ray had affixed 2 car radiators bolted together overland car radiators were used at Moulmein Burma. This was taken in Sydney, 18-verso
    - McIntosh left, Ray Parer right. In D.H.9. The "P.D." on arrival at Darwin. Aug 2nd, 1920. First single engined flight from Eng. To Aust., 19
    - Verso: McIntosh left, Ray Parer right. In D.H.9. The "P.D." on arrival at Darwin. Aug 2nd, 1920. First single engined flight from Eng. To Aust., 19-verso
    - last chapter, 20
    - Verso: last chapter, 20-verso
    - Note: Martin and Harvey [with photographs 1.22 & 1.23], 21
    - Martin and Harve, 22
    - Martin and Harve, 23
    - [Lowell Thomas and a woman standing on the stairs to a plane during the Famous First Flights], 24
    - [Lowell Thomas Jr. sitting in a broken tractor (?)], 25
    - [Lowell Thomas Jr. standing with broken farm equipment], 26
    - [Lowell Thomas Jr. sitting in a broken tractor (?)], 27
  - Subject files: Finland, 1940; 2 (Box 1544)
    - Caption: E.R.M. Verso: Winkicampague[?] Finland 1939/40 To Lowell Thomas [?] with so many thanks for his hospitality. [?], 1
    - Verso: Winkicampague[?] Finland 1939/40 To Lowell Thomas [?] with so many thanks for his hospitality. [?], 1-verso
  - Subject files: First World Flight, 1924; 3 (Box 1544)
    - Note: In 1924 eight U. S. Army airmen, years before there was a "U. S. Air Corps and then a U. S. Air Force", in four bi-planes (Douglas World Cruisers), started out to circumnavigate the globe by air. It was the greatest international air race of all time. None of the planes from the six European countries that already had entered the race, succeeded in getting more than half-way around. One American plane, The Flagship, flown by Major Frederick Martin and Sgt. Al Harvey crashed in Alaska.; These are the six flyers who made it all the way around, with L. T., historian of the flight, and Vi Moseley, for a time L. T.'s secretary. She had been secretary to Gen. Billy Mitchell, who had been rejected from the Army because his ideas were too far advanced. He knew air power would soon be predominant but his superiors, all Army Generals, were not sufficiently far-sighted enough to agree. This flight was one of the major mile-stones in the history of man, and actually launched the travel-by-air-era. World War II airmen with surplus World War II planes, launched the first aerial passenger service a year after the conclusion of this flight. America following their example in 1926.; The names of the First World Flyers were: reading from left to right: - Lt. Leslie Arnold, who later helped Eddie Rickenbacker launch Eastern Airlines; Lt. John Harding; Lt. Erik Nelson, later a Vice President of Boeing and one of the men who launched SAS; Lt. Leigh Wade, who became a World War II Air Force General; Lt. Lowell Smith, who became the Second Commander of the First World Flight and several years later was killed in Arizona; and Lt. Henry H. Ogden, who became a civilian aviation expert [Lowell Thomas, second from right], 1
    - Verso: (for Pherbie) left to right, 1-verso
    - Note: In 1924 eight U. S. Army airmen, years before there was a "U. S. Air Corps and then a U. S. Air Force", in four bi-planes (Douglas World Cruisers), started out to circumnavigate the globe by air. It was the greatest international air race of all time. None of the planes from the six European countries that already had entered the race, succeeded in getting more than half-way around. One American plane, The Flagship, flown by Major Frederick Martin and Sgt. Al Harvey crashed in Alaska.; These are the six flyers who made it all the way around, with L. T., historian of the flight, and Vi Moseley, for a time L. T.'s secretary. She had been secretary to Gen. Billy Mitchell, who had been rejected from the Army because his ideas were too far advanced. He knew air power would soon be predominant but his superiors, all Army Generals, were not sufficiently far-sighted enough to agree. This flight was one of the major mile-stones in the history of man, and actually launched the travel-by-air-era. World War II airmen with surplus World War II planes, launched the first aerial passenger service a year after the conclusion of this flight. America following their example in 1926.; The names of the First World Flyers were: reading from left to right: - Lt. Leslie Arnold, who later helped Eddie Rickenbacker launch Eastern Airlines; Lt. John Harding; Lt. Erik Nelson, later a Vice President of Boeing and one of the men who launched SAS; Lt. Leigh Wade, who became a World War II Air Force General; Lt. Lowell Smith, who became the Second Commander of the First World Flight and several years later was killed in Arizona; and Lt. Henry H. Ogden, who became a civilian aviation expert [Lowell Thomas, second from right], 2
    - U. S. ROUND THE WORLD FLIGHT PLANES ARRIVE AT DUTCH HARBOR, UNALASKA; This exclusive photograph, taken on arrival of three of the four U. S. round the world flight planes at Dutch Harbor, Unalaska, shows one of the planes after being placed on the wharf to be overhauled. The fourth, Major F. L. Martin's plane, the Seattle, was then reported missing for the first time, 3
    - Note: U. S. ROUND THE WORLD FLIGHT PLANES ARRIVE AT DUTCH HARBOR, UNALASKA; This exclusive photograph, taken on arrival of three of the four U. S. round the world flight planes at Dutch Harbor, Unalaska, shows one of the planes after being placed on the wharf to be overhauled. The fourth, Major F. L. Martin's plane, the Seattle, was then reported missing for the first time, 4
    - A handful of Americans, including consular officers and Near East Relief workers, together with French and native Syrian officials welcomed the globe encircling airmen of the United States Army on their arrival in Aleppo, Syria, after the flight across the Arabian desert from Bagdad. These pictures show the reception committee and the flyers shortly after landing on the Muslimie Aviation Field, Aleppo, outpost of French air forces in Syria, 5
    - Note: A handful of Americans, including consular officers and Near East Relief workers, together with French and native Syrian officials welcomed the globe encircling airmen of the United States Army on their arrival in Aleppo, Syria, after the flight across the Arabian desert from Bagdad. These pictures show the reception committee and the flyers shortly after landing on the Muslimie Aviation Field, Aleppo, outpost of French air forces in Syria, 6
    - Nelson and Ogden on the right [Lowell Thomas, on left], 7
    - Note: Nelson and Ogden on the right [Lowell Thomas, on left], 8
    - NEW YORK GREETS ROUND WORLD FLYERS; Photo shows left to right Gen. Patrick head of the U. S. Air Force greeting the American round the world flyers upon their arrical at New York. From left to right Gen. Patrick and Lt. Smith and Arnold. B 9-8-24, 9
    - Note: NEW YORK GREETS ROUND WORLD FLYERS; Photo shows left to right Gen. Patrick head of the U. S. Air Force greeting the American round the world flyers upon their arrical at New York. From left to right Gen. Patrick and Lt. Smith and Arnold. B 9-8-24, 10
    - ALL BOSTON CHEERS ROUND WORLD FLYERS; All Boston turned out to see the arrival of the American round the world flyers when they reached the Hub City early in the afternoon of Sept. 6 and were given a tremendous reception. Photo shows them just after they stepped on the dock being greeted by Army officials, Dwight W. Davis (straw hat, center) returning their salute. B EW FM 9-6-24, 11
    - Note: ALL BOSTON CHEERS ROUND WORLD FLYERS; All Boston turned out to see the arrival of the American round the world flyers when they reached the Hub City early in the afternoon of Sept. 6 and were given a tremendous reception. Photo shows them just after they stepped on the dock being greeted by Army officials, Dwight W. Davis (straw hat, center) returning their salute. B EW FM 9-6-24, 12
    - THE AMERICAN WORLD FLIERS AT PICTOU BAY; right to left above are shown the Hon. H. J. Logan of the Canadian Governement; Lieut. Harding, Lieut. Nelson, Commander Reid of H. M. S. Patriot and Mayor Welsford Mc Donald, son of the Minister of Defense for Canada, as they met on the deck of the "Patriot" in Pictou Bay. 9-7-24 B, 13
    - Note: THE AMERICAN WORLD FLIERS AT PICTOU BAY; right to left above are shown the Hon. H. J. Logan of the Canadian Governement; Lieut. Harding, Lieut. Nelson, Commander Reid of H. M. S. Patriot and Mayor Welsford Mc Donald, son of the Minister of Defense for Canada, as they met on the deck of the "Patriot" in Pictou Bay. 9-7-24 B, 14
    - LIEUT. WADE'S DISABLED PLANE BROUGHT ALONGSIDE CRUISER RICHMOND IN NORTH ATLANTIC; This EXCLUSIVE PHOTO shows Lieutenant Leigh Wade's disabled plane, the "Boston" being brought alongside the cruiser Richmond after being towed by the larger ship by the destroyer Billingsley. Our photo shows one of the plane's crew on the pontoon prepared to keep the plane from smashing into the ship. Shortly after, the Richmond tried to lift the plane on board. It was then that the tackle broke, the Boston falling back into the water and being smashed so badly that it had to be destroyed. B 9-1-24, 15
    - Note: LIEUT. WADE'S DISABLED PLANE BROUGHT ALONGSIDE CRUISER RICHMOND IN NORTH ATLANTIC; This EXCLUSIVE PHOTO shows Lieutenant Leigh Wade's disabled plane, the "Boston" being brought alongside the cruiser Richmond after being towed by the larger ship by the destroyer Billingsley. Our photo shows one of the plane's crew on the pontoon prepared to keep the plane from smashing into the ship. Shortly after, the Richmond tried to lift the plane on board. It was then that the tackle broke, the Boston falling back into the water and being smashed so badly that it had to be destroyed. B 9-1-24, 16
    - WITH WORLD FLYERS AT ICELAND; Lieut Nelson empties a gallon of water from his plane, the "New Orleans" at Reykjavrik, Iceland, after his successful hop from Scotland, 17
    - Note: WITH WORLD FLYERS AT ICELAND; Lieut Nelson empties a gallon of water from his plane, the "New Orleans" at Reykjavrik, Iceland, after his successful hop from Scotland, 18
    - AMERICAN ROUND-THE-WORLD FLYERS IN ENGLAND.; Photograph shows a general view taken immediately after the arrival of the American round-the-world flyers at Croydon Aerodrome, 19
    - Note: AMERICAN ROUND-THE-WORLD FLYERS IN ENGLAND.; Photograph shows a general view taken immediately after the arrival of the American round-the-world flyers at Croydon Aerodrome, 20
    - WORLD FLYERS ARRIVE AT CAPITAL AFTER FIGHTING RAIN FROM NEW YORK; The above photo shows a general view of round the world flyers at their arrival at Bolling Field, Washington D. C. The flyers arrived late due to a severe rainstorm which they fought from the time that they hopped off from New York to-day Tuesday Sept. 9-24. (B 9-9-24), 21
    - Note: WORLD FLYERS ARRIVE AT CAPITAL AFTER FIGHTING RAIN FROM NEW YORK; The above photo shows a general view of round the world flyers at their arrival at Bolling Field, Washington D. C. The flyers arrived late due to a severe rainstorm which they fought from the time that they hopped off from New York to-day Tuesday Sept. 9-24. (B 9-9-24), 22
    - WORLD FLIERS POSE AT NATIONAL MUSEUM FOR NOTED SCULPTOR; The World Fliers, the group of six army aviators whose epoch-making flight thrilled the world, have been posing for sculptor Anthony Atchinson who is making a memorial for the round-world flight. The six aviators were all at Mr. Atchinson's studio on Tuesday, December 9, when this photo was taken and the photo shows left to right, Mr. Atchinson, Lieuts. Smith, Harding, Nelson, Ogden, Wade and Arnold. FM & NY&E 12-10-24, 23
    - Note: WORLD FLIERS POSE AT NATIONAL MUSEUM FOR NOTED SCULPTOR; The World Fliers, the group of six army aviators whose epoch-making flight thrilled the world, have been posing for sculptor Anthony Atchinson who is making a memorial for the round-world flight. The six aviators were all at Mr. Atchinson's studio on Tuesday, December 9, when this photo was taken and the photo shows left to right, Mr. Atchinson, Lieuts. Smith, Harding, Nelson, Ogden, Wade and Arnold. FM & NY&E 12-10-24, 24
    - ROUND THE WORLD FLIERS REACH NEW YORK --- ENROUTE TO SEATTLE --- RECEIVE GREAT OVATION.; Photo shows-The Prince of Wales was one of the very many who waited for and welcomed the air pioneers at Mitchell Field, 25
    - Note: ROUND THE WORLD FLIERS REACH NEW YORK --- ENROUTE TO SEATTLE --- RECEIVE GREAT OVATION.; Photo shows-The Prince of Wales was one of the very many who waited for and welcomed the air pioneers at Mitchell Field, 26
    - The "New Orleans" ready for overhaul, after having been lifted from the water at Reyjavik, capital City of Iceland, August 5, 1924, 27
    - Note: The "New Orleans" ready for overhaul, after having been lifted from the water at Reyjavik, capital City of Iceland, August 5, 1924, 28
    - SCENE OF THE MISSING COMMANDER OF AMERICA'S ROUND THE WORLD FLYERS, HARBOR OF AKUTAN.; The Harbor of Akutan, in the Aleutian Islands, 350 miles West of Chignik, is the scene where Major Martin, leader of U. S. round the world flyers, is reported missing, with his flagship, "Seattle". The Akutan volcano is shown in the background. The harbor, close to the Dutch Harbor, boasts a whaling station and nine families of natives.; Photo shows whaling station in the harbor of Akutan, scene of the missing Major Martin and his round of the world plane, 29
    - Note: SCENE OF THE MISSING COMMANDER OF AMERICA'S ROUND THE WORLD FLYERS, HARBOR OF AKUTAN.; The Harbor of Akutan, in the Aleutian Islands, 350 miles West of Chignik, is the scene where Major Martin, leader of U. S. round the world flyers, is reported missing, with his flagship, "Seattle". The Akutan volcano is shown in the background. The harbor, close to the Dutch Harbor, boasts a whaling station and nine families of natives.; Photo shows whaling station in the harbor of Akutan, scene of the missing Major Martin and his round of the world plane, 30
    - FIRST PHOTOGRAPHS OF BRITISH ROUND-THE-WORLD FLYER IN SHANGHAI.; Photo shows Squadron Leader MacLaren, British round-the-world aviator, at the right, and Flying Officer Plenderleith, photographed on their arrival at Shanghai, July 3rd, 31
    - Note: FIRST PHOTOGRAPHS OF BRITISH ROUND-THE-WORLD FLYER IN SHANGHAI.; Photo shows Squadron Leader MacLaren, British round-the-world aviator, at the right, and Flying Officer Plenderleith, photographed on their arrival at Shanghai, July 3rd, 32
    - YOUNG AMERICANS CHEER ARRIVAL OF ROUND THE WORLD FLYERS; Photo shows the youngest Americans to cheer the arrival of the American Round the World flyers at Paris recently. They are the children of members of the American colony in Paris and are shown watching the planes settle. B FM 7-21-24, 33
    - Note: YOUNG AMERICANS CHEER ARRIVAL OF ROUND THE WORLD FLYERS; Photo shows the youngest Americans to cheer the arrival of the American Round the World flyers at Paris recently. They are the children of members of the American colony in Paris and are shown watching the planes settle. B FM 7-21-24, 34
    - The last picture taken of the World Fliers before they turned their planes over to the government. Commander Smith is holding onto a strut of his flagship. Standing left to right: Lieutenants Wade, Corliss Moseley, Ogden Arnold, Burdette Wright, and Nelson. Seated: Lowell Thomas, Sergeant Kennedy, Lieutenant Harding, and "Frank" the raccoon mascot. Moseley, Wright, Thomas and Kennedy were flying in escort planes., 35
    - Verso: The last picture taken of the World Fliers before they turned their planes over to the government. Commander Smith is holding onto a strut of his flagship. Standing left to right: Lieutenants Wade, Corliss Moseley, Ogden Arnold, Burdette Wright, and Nelson. Seated: Lowell Thomas, Sergeant Kennedy, Lieutenant Harding, and "Frank" the raccoon mascot. Moseley, Wright, Thomas and Kennedy were flying in escort planes., 35-verso
    - [Two planes flying in front of mountains during the First World Flight, 36
    - [A plane landing in a field during the First World Flight], 37
    - [Two men and a plane labled "Boston" in the First World Flight], 38
    - [A large crowd gathered to watch a plane land (?) during the First World Flight], 39
    - [Three men in the First World Flight standing in front of a plane], 40
    - [A group of men involved in the First World Flight gathered around a plane labled "Chicago"], 41
    - The new and old ways of traversing the ice pack in the Gulf of Finland during the winter. Enroute from Helsingfors to Stockholm, 42
    - Verso: The new and old ways of traversing the ice pack in the Gulf of Finland during the winter. Enroute from Helsingfors to Stockholm, 42-verso
    - [A plane flying over a city during the First World Flight], 43
    - [Group of women gathered around a plane during the First World Flight], 44
    - [And old ship and airplane-First World Flight], 45
    - Left to right: Martin, Lieutenants Smith, Wade, Harding and Nelson, and Sergeants Harvey, Turner, and Ogden. The original personel of the flight., 46
    - Verso: Left to right: Martin, Lieutenants Smith, Wade, Harding and Nelson, and Sergeants Harvey, Turner, and Ogden. The original personel of the flight., 46-verso
    - [Group of men and a woman looking at a globe-First World Flight], 47
  - Subject files: First World Flight, 1924; 4 (Box 1544)
    - [Lowell Thomas in an airplane during the First World Flight], 1
    - First World Fliers, 2
    - Verso: First World Fliers, 2-verso
    - [Group of men and a woman looking at a globe-First World Fliers], 3
    - [Group of men (Lowell Thomas in the middle?) during the First World Flight], 4
    - [Two planes in the First World Flight in the air attached with a cord], 5
    - [Two planes in the First World Flight in the air attached with a cord], 6
    - Verso: Make a neg. of this, 6-verso
    - [Pilot involved in the First World Flight (?) with children], 7
    - [Man in turban, holding snake], 8
    - Arrival at Kasumiguia Naval Aerodome N.E. of Tokio[Tokyo]; Fliers [?] helped to shore [?] up sailors, 9
    - Verso: Arrival at Kasumiguia Naval Aerodome N.E. of Tokio[Tokyo]; Fliers [?] helped to shore [?] up sailors, 9-verso
    - [Group of men carrying a litter], 10
    - [Picture of one plane taken from another plane during the First World Flight], 11
    - Verso: Put this plane in [?] of Persian Gulf picture, 11-verso
    - [Two men shaking hands], 12
    - L.T. in parachute harness while flying with the First World Flyers in 1924, 13
    - Verso: L.T. in parachute harness while flying with the First World Flyers in 1924, 13-verso
    - [Major Martin and Sergent Harvey men working on a plane during the First World Flight], 14
    - Verso[: The flag plane Seattle getting ready to take-off for Alaska. Major Martin kneeling and Sergent Harvey standing on the fuselage.], 14-verso
    - [Men in a row boat watching a plane in the First World Flight land], 15
    - Verso[: The arrival at Kasumigawa, just a few miles from Tokio], 15-verso
    - [A crowd of people gathered around a plane during the First World Flight], 16
    - Verso [:At Reykjavik, the New Orleans was lifted out of the water and overhauled in the street of Iceland's capital city.], 16-verso
    - [A group of men involved in the First World Flight], 17
    - Verso [: Left to right:-Lieut. Lowell H. Smith, Secretary of War John W. Weeks (?), Major General Mason M. Patrick, Brig. Gen. (?) Mitchell, Lieut. Erik H. Nelson, Lieut. Leigh Wade.], 17-verso
    - [Car with a foral banner reading "Lieut Smith".], 18
    - [Miss San Francisco welcoming a group of aviators during the First World Flight], 19
    - Verso [: "Miss San Francisco" giving Commander Lowell Smith the official kiss of welcome while the others nervously await their turn.], 19-verso
    - [Three planes in the First World Flight flying over snowy mountains], 20
    - [Airplane used in the First World Flightsinking in water], 21
    - [Plane in the First World Flight floating on the water, snowy mountains in the background], 22
    - [Airplane from the First World Flight in the water], 23
    - Verso [: After three days and four nights adrift the searchlight of the Richmond picked up Italian plane.], 23-verso
    - [Father of Lieut Smith addresses Flyers at San Diego], 24
    - Verso [: Father of Lieut Smith addresses Flyers at San Diego], 24-verso
    - [Aviators of the First World Flight receiving flowers], 25